Okay, בוקר טוב, Boker tov, today's דף daf is דף כ"ג, daf
kaf-gimmel, so 23. And we actually, it's a short דף daf because
there's a lot of practical halachic discussion, so we will have a
chance to maybe talk about some of that. So again, we're on
דף כ"ג daf kaf-gimmel and we pick up three lines in, and
I actually interrupted the ברייתא braita when we ended yesterday. The ברייתא
braita had been talking about what to do when an אב בית
דין av beit din or a נשיא nasi or חכם chacham dies.
It did not spell out full aspects of שבעה shiva and קריעה,
kriya, although the גמרא Gemara earlier had related to the idea of
doing קריעה kriya for a נשיא nasi and discussed the death of
רבן שמעון בן גמליאל, Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel, רבי's Rebbe father, and
the issue about sewing it up and so on. But here the
emphasis had more been about emptying the study halls. Again, it does
not say for what duration, but it says the בתי מדרשות batei
midrashot are בטלים, beteilim,
and spoke about a sense of a public mourning. Of course, with
the irony being that part of the aspect of mourning is that
it's not about getting together with everybody else, it's about sort of
being separated out from the community. So on that point, when the
ברייתא braita said it said נכנסים לבית הכנסת וקוראים שבעה, nichnasim l'beit
haknesset v'korim sheva, you have seven עליות, aliyot, you come to שול,
shul, right? Does it mean on שבת? Shabbos? When exactly does it
mean that you do seven עליות? aliyot? Presumably on שבת. Shabbos. But
anyway, רבינו גרשום Rabbeinu Gershom there pointed out בספר תורה דאין מתפללים
יחד בבית הכנסת אלא כל אחד ואחד מתפלל בביתו, b'sefer Torah d'ein
mitpalelim yachad b'beit haknesset elah kol echad v'echad mitpalel b'veito, right? Everybody-
so it's sort of like trying to strike this balance of a
communal observance, of people sort of getting together in some way, but
also because it's not such individuals that are recognizing what has happened,
but also maintaining the also the more sense of the loss of
community or the that occurs during this period of time. Interesting sort
of comparing this reality to the whole תשעה באב Tisha B'Av reality.
And for that we have, we'll just continue on the top of
כ"ג עמוד א', kaf-gimmel amud aleph, we have רבי יהושע בן קרחה
אומר לא שיוכלו ויתיילו בשוק, Rabbi Yehoshua ben Korcha omer lo she-yochlu
v'yitayalu bashuk, that אלא יושבין ודומין, elah yoshvin v'domim,
that when they go out, presumably to read or to have some
type of a sort of leaving of their homes in some type
of a communal way of expressing it, so it's not with, you
know, walking around in the marketplace. Presumably that wouldn't even be a
הוה אמינא, hava amina, but not with a socialization component, but everybody
is there and silent. So they're both doing it communally, but they're
doing it also without the whole social component. Okay, so that was
sort of the end of that discussion about a חכם chacham and
an אב בית דין. av beit din. And then tagged on to
the end of this ברייתא, braita, which seems to be a general
point and not limited to those types of scenarios, it says ואין
אומרים שמועה ואגדה בבית האבל. v'ein omrim shmua v'aggada b'veit ha-avel. So
forget אב בית דין av beit din or whatever, don't say- since
the larger con- since there was a whole issue here around תורה,
Torah, בתי מדרשות בטלים, batei midrashot beteilim, that seems to be the
connection, and the end of the ברייתא braita says that we don't
learn תורה Torah in the house of the אבל. avel. Now, we
had already said that an אבל avel is אסור בתלמוד תורה. assur
b'talmud Torah. We had a whole long list of things that the
אבל avel cannot do, but here presumably what this is coming to
to do is to speak about, on the one hand, שמועה ואגדה,
shmua v'aggada, which of course raises the question because we always do
say a little דבר תורה dvar Torah in the house of an
אבל avel so we could say קדיש, kaddish, and how exactly we
try to say that that's sort of, you know, falls between the
cracks, it's not real תורה Torah and so on. But here, enough
תורה Torah to be saying a קדיש, kaddish, but here שמועה ואגדה
shmua v'aggada seems to be addressing exactly that aspect, that even if
it's not, you know, a- people like in the ישיבה yeshiva they
consider hardcore תורה, Torah, not like really, you know, הלכות halachot and
so on and difficult סוגיות, sugyot, it's a- more hashkafic issues. Nevertheless,
that's also an issue. And the other thing that's important about this
is בבית האבל. b'veit ha-avel. So we're not just dealing with whether
the אבל avel can learn תורה, Torah, we're dealing with the phenomenon
that takes place in the בית האבל, beit ha-avel, maybe even if
the אבל avel isn't around, right? The אבל avel went to the-
went to the- is going off in the bathroom. Are you standing
around with your friend and שמועסן schmoozing about what you learned today
in the דף daf or you שמועס schmooze about the פרשה? parsha?
And in that way it makes sense what it's doing in this
ברייתא, braita, because the immediate response that this ברייתא braita said about
the death of a חכם chacham and a נשיא, nasi, whatever, is-
it did not refer to doing קריעה kriya or some type of
שבעה shiva observance. The real observance that this ברייתא braita spoke about
is בתי מדרשים בטלים. beit midrashim batel. So there's a sense of
like the impact of this on תורה, Torah, right? So on the
one hand, you could sort of say like this great, you know,
גדול gadol of תורה Torah is lost, so there's a sense of
תורה Torah being lost. So there's a- there's an impact in terms
of תורה Torah that takes place and so on. Here in the
case of the בית האבל, beit ha-avel, in the אבל's avel house
there isn't תורה, Torah,
you know, on the one hand it's just תורה שמחה Torah simcha
and you don't want the שמחה simcha even not in the presence
of the אבל, avel, but it's about the space and not the
אבל. avel. But it's also interesting in sort of just also thinking
about- does that mean sort of like a recognition about- about like,
you know, about when somebody is lost, the fact
that
it's... But anyway, it's interesting to see that comparison. חכם Chacham dies,
the בית מדרש Beis Medrash is בטל. Batel. A normal person dies,
you know, in the house there's no תורה. Torah. So that definitely
is what's going on in this ברייתא. Braisa. Yeah.
So a moment ago I just wanted to ask you to clarify
because so we say some דברי תורה Divrei Torah so we can
say קדיש. Kaddish. Right. They didn't say קדיש Kaddish then.
Right, that's
an interesting and good point about the whole development of the institution
of קדיש Kaddish and it only gets like one reference in the
גמרא Gemara and how that whole gets developed. So that's an excellent
point to point out. You're right that in all of our discussions
we're not talking about קדיש Kaddish and that also is what pushes
the learning of תורה Torah in the אבל'ס Avel's house which you
don't have here in the גמרא. Gemara. So I'm sure that would
be actually a fascinating issue to see when do the discussions begin
about the תורה Torah that's learned in the אבל'ס Avel's house and
you know parallel to the discussions of the development of קדיש. Kaddish.
But I assume you're right, I mean I assume that those are
going hand in hand. That's a very good point. Okay, so now
the גמרא Gemara says like this.
Now we go on to the thing that's been sort of in
the background. Sorry, last line here. אמרו עליו על רבי חנניה בן
גמליאל שהיה אומר שמועה בבית האבל. Amru alav al Rabi Chananya ben
Gamliel shehaya omer shmua be-veis ha-avel. They said about רבי חנניה בן
גמליאל Rabi Chananya ben Gamliel he would say תורה Torah in the
בית האבל. Beis HaAvel. And it sounds like the way it's being
phrased that it doesn't just mean like oh every now and then
people would catch him שמוזינג schmoozing in תורה. Torah. One wonders if
היה אומר haya omer has a sense of even in the context
of like a public teaching of תורה. Torah. Again, not in the
קדיש Kaddish sense, but you know also in the context of one
wonders ניחום אבלים, Nichum Aveilim, right? When you're doing ניחום אבלים Nichum
Aveilim do you bring I mean how do you do a ניחום
אבלים Nichum Aveilim and bringing a religious discourse? And we do find
sort of passages of ניחום אבלים Nichum Aveilim in the גמרא Gemara
where like you know you could say well you know what אהרן
Aharon died and you know you could bring in the whole you
know whole sort of תורה Torah אגדה Aggada religious discourse in the
context of your ניחום אבלים. Nichum Aveilim. And one wonders if that's
also a little bit what's going on here in this story that
he דוקא davka was אומר omer but he you know again it
sounds like he was like intentionally אומר omer not that like oh
he wasn't abiding by this rule. So a very interesting tension that
is going on there. Okay, before we continue because now we're going
to be going on to other issues I just did want to
take one second because again דף Daf is short today so we
have hopefully a little extra time. We had done yesterday the whole
issue about שמחת מרעות Simchas Mere'us which as I said is like
the biggest question that רבנים Rabbanim get שאלות shailos for, maybe not
the biggest but anyway a very constant one because it applies you
know י"ב חודש Yud-Beis Chodesh for אב ואם Av v'Eim for and
it's something that also is very hard to quantify what exactly constitutes
שמחת מרעות. Simchas Mere'us. You know the גמרא Gemara sort of spoke
about two שמחות, Simchos, general שמחה Simcha which seems to be more
problematic and שמחת מרעות Simchas Mere'us which is more like just well
no but it's a friend it's שמחה Simcha it's not just it's
not social gathering, there's a שמחה Simcha component, but it seems like
it's more about friends than about some big שמחה Simcha which presumably
you would think means like something like maybe a wedding, okay? So
that raises and in the גמרא Gemara initially distinguished between them but
by the end of the discussion it seemed to have conflated the
two of them except for some very special cases and saying that
it's an issue of שלשים Shloshim for most people and י"ב חודש
Yud-Beis Chodesh for אב ואם. Av v'Eim. So the question is like
okay well but are there like exceptions and what constitutes it and
so on and again the irony that the גמרא Gemara seems to
be saying a real שמחה Simcha is more problematic. What's a real
שמחה Simcha that's not a שמחת מרעות? Simchas Mere'us? Like I said,
wedding is the first thing that comes to mind. So does the
fact that it's a מצוה Mitzvah and make it that which makes
it a bigger deal, does that make it worse or does that
make it better because in the end it's a מצוה, Mitzvah, maybe
there should be a reason to go? So if you take a
look let's just take a look quickly at תוספות כ"ב עמוד ב'.
Tosafos Chaf-Beis Amud Beis. He says like
this. Just read one line, he says
ובמסכת שמחות U'v-Masechet Semachot it's like שמח Smach and then מות Mos
that's תוספות Tosafos with שמחות. Semachot. It's slanted through the מ. Mem.
I don't know if you see that. It's ממש mamash about exactly
halfway down that תוספות Tosafos beginning אם היה סעודת מצוה מותר. Im
haya seudat mitzvah mutar. Okay, so there's a line in שמחות Semachot
which if it was סעודת מצוה seudat mitzvah it's מותר. mutar. So
to go.
You know whole time?
Well doesn't say. לא ידענו מהו קרוי סעודת מצוה להתיר באבל. Lo
yadanu mahu karui seudat mitzvah l'hatir b'avel. אם דוקא סעודת קידוש ראש
חודש. Im davka seudat kiddush Rosh Chodesh. Okay, so I don't know
exactly what that means or doesn't mean סעודת קידוש seudat kiddush and
then ר"ח R' Ch פירש peirush I don't know it sounds like
he's saying קידוש ראש חודש. Kiddush Rosh Chodesh. They would have a
סעודה Seuda for קידוש ראש חודש. Kiddush Rosh Chodesh. Strange.
Then he says פירש אבי העזרי בשם רבינו שמשון דסעודת ברית מילה
מותר ליכנס דלא חשיבא שמחה כדאמרינן בפרק קמא דכתובות דלא אמרינן שהשמחה
במעונו משום דטרידי וליכא שמחה. Peirush Avi ha-Ezri beshem Rabbeinu Shimshon de-seudas
bris milah mutar l'hikanes d'lo chashiva simcha k'd'amrinan b'perek kama d'Kesuvos d'lo
amrinan she-hasimcha b'ma'ono mishum de-tridi v'leika simcha. Okay, ולאברהם לא פשיטא דגרע
משמחת מרעות. V'l'Avraham lo peshita d'gara m'simchas mere'us. Okay, so you know
he says so one says well you know maybe ברית מילה Bris
Milah and you know that's not so much שמחה Simcha but then
you're saying that it's less problematic than שמחת מרעות. Simchas Mere'us. You
know, is that so obvious that it's less you know you know
that it's less problematic? Maybe it's more problematic.
dealing with that and they're asking, can you eat still this issue?
Right, see, these aren't new things. Can you go ahead and eat
with the serving staff? So he says it's אסור assur ואין לחלק
בין סעודת המשמשים וסעודה עצמה. ve'ein lachaleik bein seudas hamishamshim useudah atzmah.
I'll just go ahead and eat with the service staff out there
in the kitchen. No, you can't make that distinction. Okay, ופסק דכניסה
בלא אכילה שרי דאין שמחה בלא אכילה ושתיה. upasak dechnisah belo achilah
shari de'ein simchah belo achilah ushtiyah. So you want to just go
in without eating, that's okay. ובתוספות הרא"ש פסק כלישנא דאמרי. uvTosafos haRosh
pasak kelishna de'amrei. Okay, fine. So you see all of these different
types of things, right? Is it better or is it worse because
it's a שמחת מצוה? simchas mitzvah? Is it okay to eat with
the staff? Is it okay to go there if you're not eating?
Right, so all of these are left very
un-concretized or unclarified in תוספות Tosafos and remain an ongoing issue today
in terms of that definition.
Sir, I just have a short question on the language. Who's תוספות
הרא"ש? Tosafos haRosh? What?
Where? תוספות הרא"ש. Tosafos haRosh.
Where's it say? The second to the last line.
Oh, yeah, it's presumably the Rebbe of this בעל התוספות. Ba'al haTosafos.
I don't know who it is.
And the second thing is
amidst all of the difficulty quantifying a definition, is everyone working with
a so to speak objective
occasion, like three couples want to just go out to dinner as
opposed to it's someone's birthday? Right.
So that's true, the ט"ז Taz goes even to he based on
a line in the ט"ז Taz this gets created as a really
extreme although he doesn't claim that what he's saying is definition of
שמחת מרעות, simchas mereius, but he brings down this idea of just
generally socializing and getting
together and some people who like to quantify things it becomes this
issue of not even having over more than two couples on שבת
Shabbos or something like that.
I just feel that that's a way over formalization and quantification of
something that was never defined that way but there are some people
that would like to create some very
quantifiable criteria for this because it is much more contextual. Now you
could ask very specific questions: does מצוה mitzvah make it better, does
it make it worse? But like the question
about at what stage am I getting together with friends and at
what stage is it שמחת מרעות? simchas mereius? Right, those are things
to the occasion. To the occasion. ראש חודש.
Rosh Chodesh.
Well that's also true, right that's also true. I'll just read you
one line here from the ראש, Rosh, he says like this: והקשה
הראב"ד דהכא משמע דבסעודת מצוה איכא איסורא טפי מבסעודת הרשות vehekshah haRa'avad
dehacha mashma deveseudas mitzvah ika issura tefei miveseudas hareshus because שמחה simchah
seems to be which seems to be שמחת מצוה simchas mitzvah and
that's worse than שמחת מרעות, simchas mereius, worse meaning more אסור. assur.
ובאבל רבתי תניא כל שלשים יום אסור לילך לבית המשתה עד שלשים
יום ולאביו ולאמו עד שיגערו בו חבריו, uveAveil Rabbasi tanya kol sheloshim
yom assur leileich leveiss hamishteh ad sheloshim yom ule'aviv ule'imo ad sheyiga'aru
bo chaveirav, unless,
that's interesting by the way, אביו ואמו aviv ve'imo it's not
according to מסכת שמחות Maseches Semachos it's not י"ב חודש yud beis
chodesh it's actually שיגערו בו sheyiga'aru bo until people say like, "hey
you haven't been coming to our parties recently, you have to start
coming." So that's interesting, we פוסק pasken י"ב חודש. yud beis chodesh.
But then he says אלא אם כן היתה לשם שמים. ela im
kein haysah lesheim shamayim. So אלמא דסעודת מצוה יש בה היתר יותר
מבסעודת
הרשות. alma deseudas mitzvah yeish bah heter yoseir miveseudas hareshus.
And then he goes on to try to find
exactly what the context of לשם שמים lesheim shamayim is and quotes
ירושלמי Yerushalmi about קידוש החודש, kiddush hachodesh, etc. So you see that
there's one other thing here. Oh yes, I wanted to read you
this again because of its sort of practical relevance. וכתב הרב יהודה
ברצלוני ז"ל יש שנוהגים שנכנסים בתוך י"ב חודש לבית החופה לשמוע הברכות
ולבקר, vechasav haRav Yehudah Bartzeloni zal yeish shenohagim shenichnasim besoch yud beis
chodesh leveiss hachupah lishmoa habrachos ulevakeir, right to go in to hear
have the חופה chupah to show yourself, "hi מזל טוב," mazel tov,
אבל לא יאכל. aval lo yochal. ויש שמחמירים שאין נכנסים כלל. veyeish
shemachmirim she'ein nichnasim klal.
And then he goes on to say is there שמחה simchah in
שמחת חופה simchas chupah maybe without אכילה ושתיה achilah ushtiyah and so
on.
So where were we?
בראש, baRosh, סימן מ"ב. siman mem beis.
So a lot of very relevant stuff here but not necessarily
clearly clarified or clearly quantifiable. Now we continue כ"ג kaf gimmel here
back to כ"ג עמוד א', kaf gimmel amud aleph, got five six
lines down. תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. So now what's been going on
in the background until now is this assumption that the אבל aveil
is being at home and people are coming and visiting him or
her and that the whole statement before about not going to visit
other אבלים, aveilim, but it has never been said what for us
would we probably identify as if you ask somebody what is שבעה
Shiva about? Probably the first thing somebody would say is person stays
at home for the whole week and waits and people come to
them, before you start talk about bathing or wearing shoes or all
those other types of things. That has not yet been
said as a הלכה halacha in the גמרא Gemara yet and here
we're going to actually say it as a הלכה. halacha. As I
actually said I think some people, this is just a speculation of
mine but my gut is that if you ask like random people
what does the word שבעה Shiva mean a lot of people... or
would think it means sitting in home, not שבעה, shiv'ah, seven. Okay,
so anyway, let's take a look. תנו רבנן: Tanna Rabbanan: אבל שבת
ראשונה אינו יוצא מפתח ביתו. Avel shabbas rishona eino yotzei mipetach beito.
The first שבת shabbos he does not walk out of the door
of his house. שניה, shniya, the second שבת shabbos יוצא ואינו יושב
במקומו, yotzei ve'eino yoshev bimkomo, he goes and he doesn't sit in
his normal place, doesn't exactly specify where but the assumption is we
mean in שול shul or if there's some other type of place
where, you know, people have a regular seat, like maybe a בית
מדרש beis medrash or something of that nature.
שלישית, shlishis, the third week יושב במקומו yoshev bimkomo he can sit
in his normal place ואינו מדבר ve'eino medaber but he doesn't, he's
silent, doesn't speak to anyone. רביעית, revi'is, I knew that everybody was
supposed to be quiet during דאבנינג. davening. Okay, anyway, רביעית, revi'is, the,
by the fourth שבת shabbos הרי הוא ככל אדם. harei hu kechol
adam. Then he can act like everybody else. Okay, פשוט? pashut? So
there exactly, and talking שול. shul.
No, normal. Okay, רבי יהודה אומר Rabbi Yehuda omer it is interesting,
right, because by the fourth, by the fourth שבת shabbos you're getting
towards the end of שלושים shloshim but it's not yet the end
of שלושים. shloshim. רבי יהודה אומר, Rabbi Yehuda omer, Rabbi Yehuda says
לא הוצרכו לומר שבת ראשונה לא יצא מפתח ביתו. lo hutzrechu lomar
shabbas rishona lo yetzei mipetach beito.
You don't need a הלכה halacha not to leave your house during
the first week. שהרי הכל נכנסים לביתו לנחמו. sheharei hakol nichnasim leveito
lenachamo.
That's just what of course that's what it means, meaning I that
is exactly I think getting to the point I was saying before.
It's not just a מנהג minhag of אבילות. aveilus. The basic, you
know, it's not like a הלכה halacha of אבילות. aveilus. The basic
central to the experience is, the אבל avel sits at home and
what is אבילות? aveilus? Like what's its essence, you know, as opposed
to what are its practices? So I think that, you know, I
think some of that is captured in what רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
is saying. Like you don't need a הלכה. halacha. That's what it's
about. He stays at home and everybody goes and is מנחם. menachem.
אלא שניה אינו יוצא מפתח ביתו. Ela shniya eino yotzei mipetach beito.
The הלכה halacha is that already by the third second week he's
not going, now by the way, that's got to be very challenging
for the אבל, avel, right? Nobody no longer is everybody coming to
be מנחם menachem and he's still staying at home. It's like he
doesn't have the social, any social aspect. He's really left off abandoned
almost. It's hard enough now, you know, because people are usually, hopefully
very good in terms of paying a שבעה shiva call, but often
the hardest thing for, for people, hardest, but a very hard thing
for people is like when the שבעה shiva is over, like transitioning
back into the rest of the, you know, into the normal life
and now everybody expects you to be normal, you know, and like,
and just helping with that moment of transition, right? And that's when
people aren't focusing on the person's status as an אבל. avel. So
here it's like I don't even understand how this is possible that
a person should be sort of at home with nobody coming to
be מנחם, menachem, you know, the person and still sort of being
left being sort of staying at home. Maybe you could say it's
a time for the person himself to be by him or herself
and to work through things and get ready for the transition, but
it still seems very much like a person's left abandoned in this
state. Let's read a little bit more. שלישית יוצא ואינו יושב במקומו.
shlishis yotzei ve'eino yoshev bimkomo.
By the third week he's going out and not sitting in his
place. רביעית יושב במקומו ואינו מדבר. revi'is yoshev bimkomo ve'eino medaber. By
the fourth week he's going out and not speaking to people. חמישית,
chamishis, by the fifth week הרי הוא ככל אדם, harei hu kechol
adam, he's like everybody. So now in terms of the הלכה halacha
here, just quickly if you look at תוספות, Tosafos, רבי יהודה אומר
לא הוצרכו, Rabbi Yehuda omer lo hutzrechu, ירושלמי פסק הלכה כדברי המוסיף
בימים, Yerushalmi pasak halacha kedivrei hamosif beyamim,
which is interesting because normally we say הלכה כדברי המיקל באבל. halacha
kedivrei hameikel b'avel. ואיתי Ve'isi כשהיה קטן keshehayah katan רבינו יצחק זקני
Rabbeinu Yitzchak Zikni שלא היה יושב shelo hayah yoshev
as I said, a great thing, great, about learning הלכות אבילות, hilchos
aveilus, learning this מסכת masechet is that there are so everybody's bringing
in stories. 'Cause everybody experiences it themselves and other people and so
on so there's like more case study about these issues than you're
going to find anyway in the גמרא, Gemara, in תוספות, Tosafos, in
the ראשונים. Rishonim. שהיה יושב במקומו עד שבוע רביעית, shehayah yoshev bimkomo
ad shavuah revi'is,
that he would stay in his place until the fourth week, right,
which is the second opinion here, right, and the more מחמיר machmir
one. ולא ידעתי טעמו. velo yadati taamo. שמא היה סובר כרבי יהודה,
shema hayah sover keRabbi Yehuda, if he holds like רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda which is the more מחמיר machmir position, אם כן יסבור כמותו
בשניה שאינו יוצא מפתח ביתו. im kein yisbor kemoso b'shniya she'eino yotzei
mipetach beito.
So then don't leave your house for the second week and nobody
does does that as I said that's like again in my mind
such an oppressive type of an idea. So he says nobody stays
home after the first week. So if you're already leaving the home
after the first week, how are you, why would you be practicing
like רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda about not sitting in your place? He
says מיהו יש לומר בהא אשכחן טובא לחיובא דאבילות שבעה, mihu yeish
lomar b'ha ashkechan tuva lechiyuva d'aveilus shiva, there
the concept that שבעה shiva is the end of אבילות aveilus would
override, וקיימא לן הכי. vekayma lan hachi. And now I love this
last line. וסבירא ליה טעמא כרבנן, v'sevara leih taama keRabbanan, maybe he
really פסקנס paskens like the רבנן. Rabbanan. So by the fourth week
you're allowed to, the person, what did the רבנן Rabbanan say? That
by the third week you sit in your place and you're not
מדבר, medaber, right? Is that what it says?
No, by the fourth, yeah, third week you sit in your place
and you're not מדבר. medaber. So he says ומשום דצריך לישב במקומו
ואינו מדבר, umishum d'tzarich leyshev bimkomo ve'eino medaber, since the הלכה halacha
is by the third week you sit in your place and you
don't speak, וטוב יותר שישב חוץ למקומו דשמא אין איסור לדבר כי
אם במקומו. vetov yoser sheyeishev chutz limkomo deshema ein issur ledaber ki
im bimkomo.
So he really by the third week could have sat in his
place, but then he didn't want to have to not talk. So
therefore he thinks if he doesn't sit in his place, the restriction
of talking isn't socializing, it doesn't say you go out in the
street and you can't talk to people, right? It's in the context
of like your place in שול, shul, right? Which is very much
about like your standing in the community, sort of sort of seen
as representing that. So in that context, to be speaking to other
people is very much like you've restored your full status. This is
conceptually what it's about, right? Because we're not talking about speaking, you
can't talk to people. It's when you're יושב במקומו, yoshev bimkomo, you
can't be מדבר. medaber. That's restoring your full status in the community.
So he figured, "Oh, I won't be יושב yoshev in my מקום
makom and therefore I'll still be able to talk to people." So
you see the desire to שמועס shmooze here really pushed towards a
particular, you know, תשובה teshuva choice. Yes.
This is assuming he's even talking about his place in שול. shul.
Right, I mentioned that. Who knows what מקום makom it means. But
where do you have a מקום? makom? I don't know, maybe if
it's your, maybe it's your box at the theater. I mean, I'm...
it seems to be like some type of a public. What do
you think?
Your... even in the market. Your...
oh, like in that type of thing... מקום בשוק? makom bashuk?
Move your store?
Yeah, it's true. I mean, look, the גמרא gemara is not clear
at all. We interpret it about the שול. shul. Maybe I'm obviously
probably influenced because we interpret it by the שול, shul, but I
would imagine it would have to be a place where everybody had
a different מקום makom and you had your מקום, makom, you know
what I mean? So...
but in the marketplace, it's not like everybody...
yeah,
in the marketplace, you have the... you have the buyers and they...
like it's not like everybody sits in their designated space like... so
I mean, again, like I'm not sure. To me, the marketplace sits
and in some... look, I'm obviously influenced by how I'm thinking about
it in terms of the שול. shul. But I could imagine, like
if you go to the theater and you have your, you know,
your seat at the theater, that would be a relevant application as
well. Like what?
They're talking specifically about שבת.
shabbat. Oh, so שבת ראשונה, shabbat rishona, so that's a good question
that the ראשונים rishonim discuss, which is does שבת shabbat mean שבת
shabbat or does it mean week, שבוע ראשון? shavua rishon? Because often
שבת shabbat can sometimes mean week for the duration of the first
week. So there's a major discussion in the ראשונים rishonim about whether
שבת shabbat here means שבת shabbat and whether the הלכות halachot would
be different during the rest of the week.
So if it is שבת, shabbat, that's really interesting, because they came
to do ניחום אבילים, nichum aveilim, it says here. So they were...
they were מנחם אבל. menachem avel.
Oh, so that is a good point, and I want actually to
read to you from the ראש rosh about this, and also about
how much it contrasts our... our practice. Let me just briefly read
to you from the ראש, rosh, because like I said, when you
tell people nowadays that you can do ניחום אבילים nichum aveilim on
שבת, shabbat, you know, they're like, "Shh!" right? Because again, even though
we sort of do it when we begin... we do בואי כלה
bo'i challah and then we say המקום ינחם אתכם, hamakom yenachem eschem,
but I think for most people the message is now that it's
שבת shabbat we're going to do this last ניחום nichum and we're
not going to be doing ניחום nichum on שבת. shabbat. Well, that's
right, after actually, because you do it after the... by בואי כלה.
bo'i challah.
So...
I thought it was מוצאי שבת, motza'ei shabbat, what you're saying. Oh,
it's interesting. Most people...
the...
maybe that's how, you know, again, I think that's the message people
get, but often the assumption is that the בואי כלה bo'i challah
is the acceptance of שבת. shabbat. Anyway, but I think the implicit
message is we don't do ניחום אבילים nichum aveilim on שבת, shabbat,
which is not the הלכה. halacha. So I want to just read
to you the line here from the ראש rosh about this, and
this is very much also about this question about like what does
the word שבת shabbat mean in this context. This is in סימן
מ"ו. siman mem vav. He says like this, he says...
so if you're looking, I'm gonna... it's top of the second column.
He says like this. So he discusses, שבשבת ראשונה היינו בשבוע הראשון.
deshabbos rishono hainu beshavua horishon.
So he has that whole discussion whether שבת shabbat means week or
שבת. shabbat. Anyway, he says like this. He says, וכן נוהגים באשכנז.
vechen nohagim be'ashkenaz. This is on שבת, shabbat, everything. האבל הולך לבית
הכנסת בשבת. ha'avel holech leveit haknesses beshabbos. דאחר התפילה, de'achar hatefilla,
right? So presumably on שבת shabbat after שול shul is over, שבת
shabbat morning. האבל יוצא תחילה, ha'avel yotzei techilla, ויושב לפני בית הכנסת,
veyoshev lifnei beit haknesses, וכל הקהל יוצאים ויושבים אצלו, vechol hakahal yotzim
veyoshvim etzlo, ואומר האבל והולך לביתו, va'omer ha'avel veholech leveito, וכל הקהל
הולכים עמו, vechol hakahal holchim imo, ויושבין שם שעה אחת. veyoshvin sham
sha'a achas.
So that actually they do a public ניחום אבילים nichum aveilim on
שבת. shabbat. He goes, he sits outside of שול shul after he's
been in שול shul for שבת, shabbat, everybody sits with him for
a moment right outside of שול, shul, and then they all walk
with him back home and pay a... presumably do a... sit with
him, and presumably do ניחום אבילים nichum aveilim and sit with him,
you know, at home. So there's actually a whole communal, as a
whole entire community going and doing a ניחום אבילים nichum aveilim on
שבת, shabbat, which I just found is quite fascinating, the degree that,
you know, not only that we allow it as an individual level,
but sort of the public aspect of that.
Yeah, שבת shabbat is in like the days of that week,
yeah, on שבת shabbat itself. Yeah, exactly.
But there's a debate. There's a whole discussion in the ראש. rosh.
I'll read you another line. He says like this, רבינו האי גאון
כתב, rabeinu hai gaon katav, ולעניין יוצא מפתח ביתו, ule'inyan yotzei mippetach
beito, ואפילו בשבת הכל כמנהג המדינה. va'afilu beshabbat hakol keminhag hamedina.
Because he's also talking about going... part of the context of the
ראש rosh was there was an opinion that you don't even go
to שול shul the first week. If you read שבת shabbat as
שבת shabbat literally, then it means that even on שבת shabbat during
the first week, you don't go to שול. shul. So that's part
of the issue of how to read the word שבת. shabbat. So
he was saying, "No." week, it doesn't mean שבת, Shabbat, and you
do go to שול shul on שבת Shabbat and so on. Then
he quotes רבינו האי Rabbeinu Hai says הכל כמנהג המדינה היכא דרגילי
דמצלו בבית הכנסת hakol keminhag hamedina heicha deregili demitzlu beveis haknesses where
the practice that you דאוון daven in שול, shul, מקדמי ואתי מצפרא
לבי כנישתא makdimi ve'asi mitzafra levei knishta that you should go early
be the first one there, maybe also in terms of what it
means to be going with everybody else or
not, והיכא דרגילי למיתב בביתא יתיב veheicha deregili lemeisav beveisa yativ in
places where the מנהג minhag is that he always stays at home
on שבת Shabbat he stays at home. So quite fascinating these different
מנהגים. minhagim. I'll read you from, now that I have my ספרים
sefarim here, I'll read you from, I don't have to just get
it on my iPhone to access another ספר, sefer, I'll read you
very quickly also just from some of the הלכה halacha about this
because also how absolute are these rulings in terms of not, I
mean the language is very absolute, right? אסור assur you know, he's
not יוצא מפתח
ביתו, yotzei mipetach beiso, but so
here... alright so listen, he says אבל שבוע ראשונה אין יוצא מפתח
ביתו אפילו לשמוע ברכת חופה וברכת המילה. aval shavua rishona ein yotzei
mipetach beiso afilu lishmoa birkas chuppah uvirkat hamilah.
So by the way that אפילו afilu is fascinating based on our
earlier discussion. What do you mean אפילו לשמוע ברכת המילה ברכת החופה?
afilu lishmoa birkas hamilah birkas hachuppah? Even though in the שלושים shloshim
you shouldn't be going to a שמחה. simcha. So that already, well
maybe it is allowed because you're not going to be there for
the סעודה, seudah, you know and it's a מצוה. mitzvah. That raises
all those earlier questions of definitions of שמחה. simcha. Then the רמ"א
Rema says מיהו המקל לצאת בלילה מפני הצורך לא הפסיד mihu hameikel
latzeit balayla mipnei hatzorech lo hifsid
because going out at night again is sort of less in the
sort of communal you know sort of public type of interaction with
people like you know with with all those types of normal public
you know interactions that occur. והא דאסור לצאת חוץ לביתו היינו דוקא
לטייל או למשא ומתן וכדומה. veha de'assur latzeit chutz leveiso haynu davka
letayel o lemassa umattan vechadomeh. אבל שלח מושל אחריו או שצריך
לילך בדרך aval shalach moshel acharav o shetzarich leilech baderech מושל moshel
right somehow the you know the the governor whatever the ruler of
the city needs you. או שצריך לילך בדרך או לשאר דברים הצריכים
לו הרבה. o shetzarich leilech baderech o lish'ar devarim hatzrichim lo harbeh.
הצריכים לו הרבה hatzrichim lo harbeh so this is going from one
place to another to sit שבעה shiva in a different house or
even if it's just like not סתם stam stuff it's something that's
very urgent.
כגון דבר האבוד מותר לו לצאת וכן נוהגין. kegon davar ha'avud mutar
lo latzeit vechein nohagin. Okay so again you know when the גמרא
Gemara sounds very absolute, we start seeing various latitudes even like when
it's not so urgent just like a difference of going out at
night where there's less of a social component, right? It's not supposed
to be the home is a prison, right? So it's a that
whole very interesting and then it goes on different types of you
know possible exceptions and limits to this. Okay so now again that's
a very like I said it's so funny that until now you
know this wasn't even listed in the list of מנהגי אבל. minhagei
avel. But part of that might have to do with what רב
יהודה Rav Yehuda says, like this is exactly what sitting שבעה shiva
is about. Okay now moving on to another פתח petach aspect. תנו
רבנן tanu rabbanan כל שלושים יום לנישואין. kol shloshim yom lenissuin. All
for thirty days a person cannot get married. Now this is all
going to be very much sort of said as no surprise from
the man's perspective, we'll talk about the woman's perspective a little bit.
I mean the הלכה halacha of not getting married all thirty days
is the same, but some of these exceptions are or these exceptions
we're about to talk about are from the man's perspective.
מתה אשתו meta ishto now by the way right the whole issue
about before well okay מתה אשתו meta ishto if a man's wife
dies אסור לישא אשה אחרת עד שיעברו עליו שלש רגלים. assur lissa
isha acheret ad sheya'avru alav shalosh regalim. So if then you have
to wait if a man's wife dies then forget the fact that
okay you know other שמחות simchos the person could do after שלושים.
shloshim. But in terms of like respect of his first wife he
should not get married again until after שלש רגלים. shalosh regalim.
Now so it's not about not exactly מנהגי אבילות minhagei aveilus as
much as respect of his first wife or other possible things that
we'll see because the actual again שמחה simcha ends after thirty days
issues. רב יהודה אומר Rav Yehuda omer רגל ראשון ושני אסור שלישי
מותר. regel rishon vesheni assur shelishi mutar. By the third one it's
permissible presumably he means after two רגלים regalim it's permissible. אם אין
לו בנים מותר לישא לאלתר im ein lo vanim mutar lissa le'altar
and if he has no children then he can get married right
away because of the מצוה mitzvah of פרו ורבו. pru urevu. משום
ביטול פרו ורבו. mishum bittul pru urevu. הניחה לו בנים קטנים henicha
lo vanim ktanim or if he's left with small kids and the
assumption is that he's not capable of raising them himself, so מותר
לישא לאלתר. mutar lissa le'altar. He can also get married right away
מפני פרנסתם mipnei parnasatam in order to support them or to you
know to raise them.
If he has daughters, no sons, that's also...
in terms of the first statement presumably because it's not a קיום
kiyuum yet of פרו ורבו. pru urevu. Now what does לאלתר le'altar
mean? לאלתר le'altar you would think means maybe it means after שבעה,
shiva, right? But let's take a look at this story. מעשה שמתה
אשתו של יוסף הכהן. ma'aseh shemeta ishto shel Yosef HaKohen. There's a
story that the wife of יוסף הכהן Yosef HaKohen died ואמר לאחותה
בבית הקברות ve'amar la'achosa beveit hakevarot and he said to her sister
in the like in the right there in the cemetery during the
קבורה. kevura. לכי ופרנסי את בני אחותך. lechi ufarnasi es bnei achoseich.
Come and support the children of your sister, your sister's you know
your nieces and nephews. He basically proposed to her in the בית
הקברות. beis hakevaros. ואף על פי ve'af al pi ואף על פי
כן *v'af al pi kein* and even so לא lo, בא עליה
אלא לזמן מרובה *lo ba aleha ela l'zman meruba*. So that was
okay, it was allowed in order that she should be able to
raise the kids, but you know there still is fundamentally an issue
of the שמחת נישואין *simchas nisuin* that is problematic, which a lot
has to do with the actual, you know, coming together of husband
and wife, having sex. So that he did not, he waited. How
long did he wait? מאי לזמן מרובה *mai l'zman meruba*? אמר רב
פפא לאחר שלושים יום *amar Rav Pappa le-achar shloshim yom*. He waited
30 days because that is the period of שמחה simcha. *simcha*. So
on the one hand there was an allowance, even more radical, you
don't have to wait שלוש רגלים *shalosh regalim*, שני רגלים *shnei regalim*
or whatever because of these issues. On the other hand, there was
you know, since it was about raising the kids and there is
generally an issue of the sort of שמחה simcha, *simcha* and related
aspects of marriage, he waited for the first, he waited till the
end of the month. What would have happened in a case where
it was about פרו ורבו Peru U'rvu, *p'ru u'rvu* where obviously if
it's about פרו ורבו Peru U'rvu, *p'ru u'rvu* and that's what the
allowance is about then they need to be having sex. So you
know, תוספות Tosafos *Tosafos* says that basically in that case you would
allow to have sex right you know as soon as the marriage
occurred if it was the first case of פרו ורבו Peru U'rvu
*p'ru u'rvu*. Now there's a long תוספות Tosafos *Tosafos* where, or actually
it's a short תוספות Tosafos, *Tosafos*, long תוספות Tosafos *Tosafos* elsewhere, long
ראש *Rosh*, long discussion, where basically
he's very bothered by the sentence in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* that
it could be done even during שבעה shiva, *shiva*. And he tries
to say that the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is, it's exaggerated. When it
says בית הקברות *beiss hakvaros* it meant like metaphoric בית הקברות *beiss
hakvaros*. It didn't literally do it in the cemetery. Or he says
he proposed in the cemetery but they didn't actually get married till
after the שבעה shiva *shiva*. Okay, he's just very bothered by the,
you know, I mean the גמרא's Gemara *Gemara's* pretty, you know, pretty
like it sticks in your head. He proposed to her in the
cemetery,
apparently. But anyway, but תוספות Tosafos *Tosafos* is really bothered by that
and based on other סוגיות sugyos *sugyos* or whatever and he wants
to say or just bothered by it intrinsically and that it's after
the שבעה shiva. *shiva*. That's one point. There's also a lot of
discussion about somebody who like
you know is,
has already been מקיים פרו ורבו mekayeim Peru U'rvu, *mekayem p'ru u'rvu*
but other, wait let me let me hold on to that for
second. I want to just look at a very fascinating תוספות Tosafos,
*Tosafos* of עד שיעברו ג' רגלים *ad she-ya'avru gimmel regalim*. So one
is the question about the exceptions but let's first look at the
general rule here and the idea of שלוש רגלים *shalosh regalim*. So
take a look at תוספות Tosafos *Tosafos*, he says עד שלוש רגלים
בלא שמחה simcha *ad shalosh regalim belo simcha*. What's the reason of
waiting שלוש רגלים *shalosh regalim*, right? It's not an idea of יב
חודש *yud bais chodesh*, it's not an idea of שלושים יום *shloshim
yom*, you know, so what is this about? So he says there
should be שלוש רגלים בלא שמחה simcha, *shalosh regalim belo simcha*, right?
ושמחת אתה וביתך *v'samachta ata u'veisecha*, right? So there should be שלוש
רגלים בלא שמחה simcha, *shalosh regalim belo simcha* so there's not the
same שמחה simcha *simcha* that you have when it's not a full
family. ולא ישכח אהבת אשתו *v'lo yishkach ahavas ishto*. So reason number
one is, you know, out of the respect to his wife and
the marriage and the relationship, it should not be so you know
he should sort of stick with him. So it's funny like they've
been together for 20 years but will stick with him is that
sense of loss over שלוש רגלים *shalosh regalim*, you know, and he
remembers how hard that was during those first שלוש רגלים *shalosh regalim*.
That's one explanation, right? You know it's funny it just doesn't seem
to be to honor his wife's memory but anyway לא ישכח *lo
yishkach* is that presumably it's a similar concept אהבת אשתו *ahavas ishto*.
אי נמי *ee nami*, right? כדי שישא אשה אחרת ולא יהיה זכור
מן הראשונה שלא יהיה שתי דעות במיטה *kdei she-yisa isha acheres v'lo
yihiyeh zachur min ha-rishona she-lo yihiyeh shtei deios b'mita* which is a
concern the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* has. If it's still so soon after
his first marriage then when he's now together with his second wife
he'll still be thinking about his first wife. So and while they're
having sex which is particular like a גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* type of
a virtual adultery. So the problem is not respect of the first
wife, it's don't do it so quick to respect the second wife
so that you're not, it's not still in the person's head, you
know, mind.
ועוד *v'od* that she should not forget,
ועוד *v'od*
right, exactly, you should remember the past you shouldn't have an active
memory in the present. ועוד פן יזכירנה אהבת אשתו לקנטרה *v'od pen
yazkirena ahavas ishto l'kantra*.
Okay, that maybe it won't just be accidentally the guy is still
thinking about his first wife but when like the second wife now
burns the food or whatever or makes a meal he says, "Ah,
you know, my first wife she made such better, you know, her
soup was so much better," you know, or she whatever. So you're
constantly mentioning the first wife to the second one and that's also
so again hopefully you wait שלוש רגלים *shalosh regalim* and some of
those memories have faded a bit. So of course he points out
are you supposed to have the memory fade or you supposed to
have the memory stick? Anyway then he has a fascinating point here
at the end. He says like this,
he says like this, פירש הרב רבינו יונה דאין שייך לפסוק כרבי
k'Rabbi. יהודה Yehuda דאמר שני רגלים *peireish ha-rav Rabbeinu Yonah d'ein shayach
lifsok k'Rabbi Yehuda d'amar shnei regalim*. Why don't we be lenient and
say שני רגלים *shnei regalim* not שלוש *shalosh*? הלכה halacha, כדברי המיקל
באבל *halacha k'divrei ha-meikal b'avel* שיבוש דקיימא לן הלכה כדברי המיקל באבל
*shibush d'kaima lan halacha k'divrei ha-meikal b'avel*. Don't say that. דהני מילי
דפליגי בהכא אין זו באבל *d'hani mili d'pligi b'hacha ein zu b'avel*
דימי אבל avel. כלו להן *d'yimei eivel kalu lahen*. The idea of
waiting two or three רגלים *regalim* is not a הלכות אבילות hilkhos
avelus *hilchos aveilus*. The guy's done with אבילות Avelus *aveilus*. It's thirty
days. There's no longer מנהגי אבילות avelus *minhagei aveilus*. This is a
הלכה *halacha* of respecting your first wife or respecting your second wife,
okay, whatever the concerns are, but it's not a הלכה *halacha* in
הלכות halachos אבילות avelus *hilchos aveilus*. So fascinating right, sort of pinpointing
exactly that subject, that's why you could talk about שני רגלים *shnei
regalim*, שלוש רגלים *shalosh regalim*, it's not about הלכות אבילות avelus *hilchos
aveilus*.
Anyway, those issues I think are fascinating, the different types of concerns.
Again, of course, this is all from the man's perspective. What about
the woman? In general, it's said that the woman waits thirty days.
Interesting question about, here's the interesting question, right, so in all these
things about the fact that maybe she needs a husband to help
her raise her kids, she's not raising them alone, or whatever, those
types of things, or פרו ורבו, halachically she's not מצווה metzuveh in
פרו ורבו, fascinating that those types of things are
not dealt with. Not fascinating, I mean, maybe to be expected, but
it's interesting that those are not sort of seen as exceptions. There
are interesting cases where the issue is that somebody was engaged, the
woman was engaged, the man was a first wedding, so he wasn't
yet מקיים פרו ורבו, mekayeim Peru U'rvu, and then she became an
אבל. avel. Would we let her get married during the שלשים shloshim
in order to help him be מקיים פרו ורבו, mekayeim Peru U'rvu,
right? Because it's sort of like his, halachically it's his קיום kiyum
of פרו ורבו, but she's the one that's the אבל. avel. So
you could well, just get married to someone else if you want
to be מקיים פרו ורבו, mekayeim Peru U'rvu, but actually you see
the ראשונים rishonim saying like, look, reality is he's only going to
marry her, he wants to marry her. So then they say, oh,
so in order to let him be מקיים פרו ורבו, we'll let
her get married during her שלשים. shloshim. So it becomes a whole
interesting thing about dealing with this because all these things are sort
of around the man, either the man's מצוה mitzvah פרו ורבו or
the man's inability to raise the kids on his own, like it
never sort of looks at those issues from the woman's perspective. Okay,
yes, you had a question?
Maybe I'm not understanding the story. There's a כהן Kohen in a
graveyard?
Yeah, because for his wife and for his relatives, you are מטמא.
metamei. כהן Kohen is מטמא metamei for his שבעה קרובים. shiva krovim.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this. תנו רבנן. Tanu
Rabbanan. כל שלשים יום לגיהוץ. kol shloshim yom legihutz. All thirty days,
the whole idea of not presumably although there's conflicting evidence about this,
but presumably the idea of not laundering clothes is only for a
week, like not getting a haircut and bathing and so on. But
for the rest of the month, there's an idea of not doing
גיהוץ, gihutz, which we would sort of call like dry cleaning, like
very good type of a cleaning of the clothes. So that applies
for all thirty days, dry cleaning. אחד כלים חדשים ואחד כלים ישנים,
echad keilim chadashim ve'echad keilim yeshanim, whether new clothes or old clothes,
because old clothes even if you dry clean them, they don't really
look new again. But nevertheless, it's all a problem. יוצאים מתוך המכבש,
yotzim mitoch hamachbesh, if they come from outside of the press, like
they get repressed and whatever and they look fresher, that's a problem.
רבי אומר לא אסרו אלא כלים חדשים בלבד, Rabbi omer lo asru
ela keilim chadashim bilvad, only new clothes, right, you're never going to
get old clothes even after a dry clean to look new, so
the only real problem is new clothes. So you get your new
clothes dry cleaned and it looks like you're wearing like it's totally
like new clothes. Not totally new, obviously. בלבד. bilvad. רבי אלעזר ברבי
שמעון אומר לא אסרו אלא כלים חדשים לבנים בלבד, Rabbi Elazar b'Rabbi
Shimon omer lo asru ela keilim chadashim levanim bilvad, only white new
clothes, because then it looks totally like fresh and new, assuming if
you could get it back to white again and sparkling. Okay, anyway,
אביי נפק בגרדא דסרבלא Abaye nafik begarda desarvela כרבי. Abaye went out
with some type of a old white like a cloak, like Rabbi,
because it wasn't new, so he figured it was okay, right,
even. רבא נפק בחימוצתא דרומיתא סומקתא חרתי. Rava nafik bechimutzta d'romita sumakta
charti. Rava went out with this type of a cloak of
a red Roman cloak, which was new, so even though it was
new he wore it כרבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון, k'Rabbi Elazar b'Rabbi Shimon,
since it wasn't white, like Rabbi Elazar b'Rabbi Shimon. So basically the
actual parameters of wearing freshly dry cleaned clothes during שלשים shloshim is
very narrow here. That being said, you see this huge תוספות because
there's other סוגיות sugyos, that seem to sound like there's an איסור
issur of laundering for thirty days, not just for the week. And
תוספות tries to figure out how to read those other סוגיות, maybe
they weren't they didn't literally mean laundering, they meant גיהוץ. gihutz. Maybe
actually גיהוץ gihutz here doesn't just mean dry cleaning, maybe גיהוץ gihutz
means laundering with soap and when it says laundering is the first
week it just meant without soap, or with soap that constitutes גיהוץ.
gihutz. And then there's other discussions because other גמרות Gemaros make it
sound that outside of ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael we don't know how
to do גיהוץ gihutz to the same degree when they would soap,
so therefore nothing counts as גיהוץ gihutz outside of ארץ ישראל, Eretz
Yisrael, which would mean that everything is permissible after שלשים. shloshim. So
there's all of these discussions, but the reality is as you can
see from this story that the actual הלכה, it's very limited what's
אסור assur for the rest of the month and it remains conflicted
in the שולחן ערוך Shulchan Aruch as well, with it being but
clearly being like very limited what's אסור assur in this category after
the first month.
Okay, what would have been done in the Middle Ages that would
correspond to what we're referring to?
I have no idea. The history, ironing?
I just irony?
I have no idea. I have no idea the history of laundry
in the time of חזל, Chazal, in the Middle Ages. There's a
huge סוגיא. sugya. There's a huge סוגיא sugya about גיהוץ שלנו ככיבוס
שלהן. gihutz shelanu k'kibbus shelahen. I know somebody I think somebody I
think somebody did a doctoral dissertation on it, okay, I don't know.
Let's go on. המשנה, Hamishnah, שבת עולה ואינה מפסקת. Shabbos olah v'einah
mafsekes. Okay,
so back finally to the משנה. mishnah.
שבת Shabbos counts towards the שבעה, shiva. but it does not interrupt,
right? Obviously because every שבעה runs through שבת. Shabbos. Sorry,
meaning it doesn't interrupt, it doesn't end the שבעה. בני יהודה בני
גליל. Bnei Yehuda Bnei Galil. Now this is fascinating. We're going to
have a debate, not by any rabbis, but by two different geographic
regions, יהודה and the גליל, Galil, and different sort of practices that
they had. So it's not necessarily that they're issuing halakhic rulings here;
we're talking about different practices that they had. Okay, but the גמרא
Gemara. is going to sort of treat it as a verbalized halakhic
debate. הני אמרי, Honey amri, these say, okay, יש אבילות בשבת. yesh
avelus beShabbos. אבילות avelus continues to be practiced on שבת. Shabbos. והני
אמרי, Ve'honey amri, and those say, interesting who's who, אין אבילות בשבת.
ein avelus beShabbos. It doesn't... it isn't practiced on שבת. Shabbos. Now
what does it mean those that say it is practiced? Do they
mean it's fully practiced, like everything? Like so as we know, and
as the גמרא gemara is going to conclude in tomorrow's דף, daf,
there is... we פוסקין pasken דברים שבצנעה נוהג. devarim she'betzina noheg. That
private forms of practicing of the אבילות avelus is what we're talking
about. Not having sex, maybe not bathing, things that are... don't sort
of announce to other people that somebody is an אבל. aveil So
תוספות, and based on רש"י Rashi also, want to read it this
way, that the debate is whether a person continues to practice דברים
שבצנעה. devarim she'betzina. The גמרא gemara doesn't say that. It's possible to
read it, and it's a fascinating question, were there maybe those that
actually practiced full אבילות avelus during שבת? Shabbos? And why not? If
רגל regel is מפסיק mafsik and is more powerful, why is רגל
regel מפסיק? mafsik? Because רגל regel is about שמחה. simcha So שבת
Shabbos isn't מפסיק; mafsik; it's because we're acknowledging that שבת Shabbos isn't
about שמחה, simcha, right? We don't think about שמחה simcha, in terms
of שבת. Shabbos. כבוד, Kovod, עונג, onneg, etc. So שבת Shabbos isn't
about שמחה, and therefore it's not מפסיק, mafsik, so why is it
clear that it would have a power to limit אבילות avelus, at
all? Maybe full אבילות avelus should be practiced. Now, of course תוספות
quotes the reason not is because it might not be about שמחה,
but it's also not about צער, tza'ar, it's about כבוד, kovod, עונג,
onneg, enjoyment, and so on, and that's not consistent with a lot
of the practices about אבילות avelus that put a person in a
sort of... in a more pained mindset so...
or discomfort and so on. But it's not as evident that you
could have this middle thing, like if it doesn't have the power
of שמחה to be מפסיק, mafsik, maybe אבילות aveilus, should be practiced.
It's possible to understand that that actually is what's being articulated. Again,
רש"י Rashi and תוספות sort of pull back from that and they
say to the degree that anybody is saying you do אבילות בשבת,
avelus beShabbos, it's our understanding of that, which means דברים שבצנעה, devarim
she'betzina, okay. But again, not clear in the גמרא. gemara The גמרא
gemara says there's an opinion you do אבילות, aveilus who knows what
that means? Let's continue. Okay. Yes.
Let me just add one second. He says, that's a really interesting
point. The question is whether these practices are supposed to reflect or
create.
Right.
Yeah, that's an excellent point, and I think both are true. What?
That was a question, yes. Well, what do you think?
There tends to be... both tend to be said. So רב סולובייצ'יק,
Rav Soloveitchik, certainly one of his major תורות Torahs about הלכות אבילות
aveilus,
is seeing these not just as practices but as expressions of an
inner experience and sort of focusing on the importance of that inner
experience. And at the same time, for a lot of people the
whole power in general of ritual and various practices is that it
helps cultivate and nurture a type of... it helps one internalize certain
things. Now, you could say some people don't need it, but some
people do need it during אבילות aveilus, actually to help sort of
ground them and put them in touch. So I think... I would
not sort of choose between those two. I think both are true.
In terms of the power of שבת Shabbat and this middle state
that it's not שמחה but it's something,
if you take a look at תוספות, the המאן תוספות, ha-man Tosafos,
like about right before the new תוספות ואינו, Tosafos ve'eino, and you
go up a line, he says
like this: אבל כדי שישבת עולה רגל אינו עולה הלא אין אבילות
כלל משום דכתיב ושמחה, Aval kadei she-Shabbat oleh regel ein oleh... halo
hein avelus klal mishum de'ketiv ve-simcha, that's by רגל. regel. שבת מיהו
לא כתיב שמחה אפילו אינו נוהג בה עולה. Shabbat mi-lo ketiv simcha,
afilu eino noheges oleh. ובירושלמי מפרש טעמא דשבת דאין אבילות נוהג בו,
Uve-Yerushalmi mefarash ta'ama de-Shabbat d'ein avelus noheg bo, there's no שמחה, משום
דכתיב ברכת ה' היא תעשיר ולא יוסיף עצב עמה. mishum de'ketiv birchas
Hashem hi sa'ashir velo yosif etzev imah. The blessing of God makes
one rich or whatever, and there's no pain or suffering. ובשבת כתיב
ביה ברכה. Uve-Shabbat ketiv bei bracha. So okay, it might not be
שמחה, but it's not a day to be suffering either, okay? So
that's that interesting middle position of שבת. Shabbat. So let's go back
in the גמרא. gemara So do... does one נוהג אבילות noheg avelus
on שבת Shabbos or not? And what again נוהג אבילות noheg avelus
means, could be full, could be דברים שבצנעה. devarim she'betzina. מאן דאמר
יש אבילות בשבת, Man d'amar yesh avelus beShabbos, the one who says
אבילות aveilus is practiced on שבת, Shabbos, דתני עולה, de'tani oleh, because
it's counting towards the שבעה. So it must be that it's being
practiced, at least to some degree. מאן דאמר אין אבילות בשבת, Man
d'amar ein avelus beShabbos, it's not practiced, דתני אינה מפסקת, de'tani eina
mafsekes, it's not interrupting. So if it doesn't have the power to
interrupt, okay. Now what does that mean? Maybe that's because you're נוהג.
noheg. No. אי סלקא דעתך יש אבלות Aveilus בשבת *i salka deitach
yeish aveilus b'shabbos*, if you would really be practicing אבלות בשבת *aveilus
b'shabbos* fully or maybe even partially, so but if it was really
being practiced, הא אבלות נהגא *ha aveilus naga*, איפסק מיבעיא *ipsek mibei'ah*?
The Mishnah went ahead to tell you it doesn't interrupt. If it's
continued to be practiced on Shabbos, of course it doesn't interrupt. The
fact that the Mishnah needs to tell you it doesn't interrupt the
אבלות *aveilus*, you know, in terms of stopping the שבעה *shiva*, is
only because it's not being practiced during Shabbos. Okay. So that's the
two opinions. So now the גמרא gemara *Gemara* says, ואלא הא דתני
עולה *ve-ela ha de-tani ola*, what do you do with the fact
that the Mishnah says it counts and according to you it's not
being practiced? Well why is the Mishnah saying that it counts towards
Shabbos if, counts towards the שבעה *shiva* if אבלות *aveilus* isn't being
practiced? No, איידי דקבעי למיתני סיפא אינו עולה *aidi d'ka'baei le-mitni seifa
eino oleh*, since it's going to say by the רגלים *regalim* that
they don't count, תנא רישא reisha עולה *tana reisha ola*, so in
the beginning it says it does count. But the reality is, you
know, it's not being practiced. Now the funny thing is, is that
the question, and this is what big Tosafot trying to figure out,
the question should not be about the language of the, of the
Mishnah, it should be about the הלכה *halacha* of the Mishnah, right?
You could say, oh, the reason it says עולה *ola* by שבת
shabbos *Shabbos* is because it's going to say אין עולין *ein olin*
by the רגלים *regalim*. Fine. But the question still is, why does
it count towards the שבעה *shiva* if nothing is being practiced? So
the answer might be that, that look, it's one thing to say
that, you know, שבעה *shiva* ends a week after it starts and,
and you don't have, so you count it seven days from the
day it starts. That's one thing, I don't have a problem with
that. Maybe there's no practice of אבלות *aveilus* on שבת shabbos. *Shabbos*,
but nevertheless שבעה *shiva* is a week from the day it starts.
But to say שבת shabbos? *Shabbos* is עולה *ola* seems to be
suggesting that there's a practice done on שבת shabbos. *Shabbos* that get,
you get credit for as it were and that counts towards it,
not just that, you know, the שבעה *shiva* ends a week later.
So he says that's what bothers me. The language of עולה *ola*,
the language suggests that there's some practice that is counting towards the
שבעה *shiva*. And then the response is don't get hung up on
the language. The language of עולה *ola* is only because by the
רגלים *regalim* it's going to say אין עולין *ein olin*. But the
reality is there's no practice taking place on שבת shabbos. *Shabbos*. So
that's one opinion. ולמאן דאמר יש אבלות בשבת *u-le-man d'amar yeish aveilus
b'shabbos*, according to the opinion there is אבלות *aveilus* on שבת shabbos
*Shabbos*, הא קתני אינה מפסקת *ha katani einah mafseketh*, why did the
Mishnah have to say it doesn't interrupt? I mean if שבעה *shiva*
is being practiced, of course nothing is going to interrupt. So same
answer, משום דקבעי למיתני סיפא מפסיקין *mishum d'ka'baei le-mitni seifa mafsikin*, since
we're going to say by the רגלים *regalim* they do interrupt, תנא
רישא אינה מפסקת *tana reisha einah mafseketh*, you say by שבת shabbos
*Shabbos* it doesn't interrupt even though it's obvious it doesn't interrupt according
to this opinion because it still is being practiced. Okay, so we
still have this debate, is אבלות *aveilus* practiced on שבת shabbos, *Shabbos*?
And again, does it mean fully practiced, does it mean partially practiced,
not clear. But it's a debate whether אבלות *aveilus* is being practiced
on שבת shabbos. *Shabbos*. לימא כתנאי *leima ki-tanna'ei*, let's say this is
like a debate of תנאים *tanna'im*. מי שמתו מוטל לפניו mutal lefanav.
*mi she-meiso mutal le-fanav*, somebody who's dead body is in front of
him, אוכל בבית אחר *ochel b'vayis acher*. Now this is about אונן
onein *onen* and what's like sort of surprising about this גמרא Gemara,
*Gemara* is that this גמרא Gemara *Gemara* assumes that there is some
identity or some parallel between practices of אנינות aninut. *aninus* and practices
of אבלות *aveilus*, which normally are kept very, very separate. This גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* thinks you can learn one from the other. And I'll
just tell you, there's a major מחלוקת ראשונים Rishonim *machlokes rishonim*. There's
תוספות *Tosafot* which if I forget I think it's a ריט"א *Rit-i*
that basically says these are completely different states and have nothing to
do with one another. And then there's an approach of the רמב"ם
*Rambam* that because of גמרות *gemaros* like this suggests that אנינות aninut
*aninus* and אבלות *aveilus* is all fundamentally one state, it's just that
during the period of אנינות aninut. *aninus* because of the need to
take care of the מת meis *meis*, that the, that demands certain
additional practices, like not eat, you know, eating meat, drinking wine, other
types of things, obviously not doing ברכות brachos *brachos* and מצוות *mitvos*
etc. But it also allows other things, like it allows you to
put on your shoes because you got to be do and to
bathe or whatever because you got to be focusing on the מת
meis *meis* and therefore we're giving you more latitude in terms of
some of those other things. But all of that is like overrides,
fundamentally it's a consistent state from the time of death, you know,
through the end of שבעה *shiva*. That's an idea of the רמב"ם
*Rambam*, it's much more complicated but he because of גמרות *gemaros* like
this wants to see a basic continuity between those two with sort
of special overrides that might occur during אנינות aninut, *aninus*. Okay, so
yeah.
Was it always understood there was no אנינות aninut *aninus* on שבת
shabbos. *Shabbos*?
Well, let's take a look about the issues of אנינות aninut *aninus*
on שבת *Shabbos*. Let's take a look. לימא כתנאי *leima ki-tanna'ei*, let's
say that this is debate linked to a debate of תנאים *tanna'im*.
מי שמתו מוטל לפניו mutal lefanav. *mi she-meiso mutal le-fanav*, somebody's dead
body's in front of him, meaning he's in a status of אונן
onein *onen*, אוכל בבית אחר *ochel b'vayis acher*, has to eat in
another house, doesn't eat in the presence of the מת *meis*. אין
לו בית אחר *ein lo bayis acher*, אוכל בבית חבירו *ochel b'vayis
chaveiro*. He doesn't have another house, he goes to his friend's house.
אין לו בית חבירו *ein lo bayis chaveiro*, doesn't have a friend's
house, עושה לו מחיצה עשרה טפחים *oseh lo mechitzah asarah tefachim*, he
makes a little barrier ten handbreadths so he's in a different zone.
אין לו דבר לעשות מחיצה *ein lo davar la'asoth mechitzah*, if he
doesn't even have the means of doing that, מחזיר פניו ואוכל *machzir
panav v'ochel*. Okay, he turns his back to the מת *meis*, he
doesn't literally, you know, have chewing in front of the מת *meis*,
it's not respectful. ואינו Ve'eino. מיסב ואוכל mesev ve'ochel, *v'eino meisav v'ochel*,
he doesn't recline, which is a very like, you know, כבודיק *kovodik*
and relaxed way, obviously his focus should be on the מת *meis*,
not getting too much into his סעודה *seudah*. ואינו אוכל בשר ואינו
שותה יין *v'eino ochel basar v'eino shotheh yayin*, doesn't eat meat or
drink wine, right? Obviously that would be, you know, too indulgent, and
also maybe drawing them, him away from his focus or her focus
on the מת. ואין מברך ואין מזמן, ve'ein mevarech ve'ein mezamein, doesn't
make ברכות brachos. and doesn't do זימון zimun and here we get
the idea of the override of מצות mitzvot and even the override
of ברכות. brachos, ואין מברכין עליו ואין מזמנין עליו, ve'ein mevarchin alav
ve'ein mezamnin alav, you don't even include him in a זימון. zimun.
Question about what מברכין עליו mevarchin alav means that's different from מזמנין
עליו. mezamnin alav. But okay, doesn't get included in a זימון. zimun.
ופטור מקריאת שמע ומן התפילה ומן התפילין ומכל מצות האמורות בתורה, u'patur
mikrias shema u'min hatfillah u'min hatfillin u'micol mitzos ha'amuros batorah, exempt from
קריאת שמע, krias shema, prayer, תפילין tfillin and all מצות mitzos in
the Torah.
So long as מתו מוטל לפניו... meiso mutal lefanav...
yeah... well, whenever a מת is buried it is conceptually מוטל לפניו.
mutal lefanav Now there is interesting questions about people that are in
a different city and are not in the process or whatever, right,
so that's questions of exactly what status makes it considered מוטל לפניו.
mutal lefanav And it's bigger than...
it's bigger than לא ילעג לרש. lo yilag laraush.
Yeah, yeah, yeah. This is a status
of אנינות. aninut Okay. The רישא of eating is literally right. No,
that's clear, that is clear that in this in this state מוטל
לפניו starts out as something very concrete and then not eating is
not eating literally in the presence, but then it becomes more abstracted
to the status of אנינות which is a conceptual status of מוטל
לפניו and then it becomes questions of who exactly is in that
category. Now,
ובשבת, uv'shabbos, but on שבת where you can't do burial anyway, so
the idea of being focused on the burial is different. מיסב ואוכל,
you can do הסבה, aseibah, אוכל בשר ושותה יין, ochel basar v'shoseh
yayin, meat and wine, ומברך ומזמן ומברכין ומזמנין עליו וחייב בקריאת שמע
ובתפילה ובתפילין ובכל מצות האמורות בתורה. u'mevarech u'mezamein u'mevarchin u'mezamnin alav v'chayav
bikrias shema u'vitfillah u'vitfillin u'vchol mitzos ha'amuros batorah. Do מצות, mitzos, do
ברכות, etc. Of course תפילין tfillin is thrown in there because you
don't put on תפילין tfillin on שבת. Okay. רבן גמליאל אומר, Rabban
Gamliel omer, מתוך שנתחייב באלו, mitoch shenischayev be'elu, ah, once you're חייב
chayav in all those other מצות, mitzvos, נתחייב בכולן, nis-chayev b'chulan, then
you're חייב chayav in everything. Isn't that what we just said, you're
חייב chayav in everything on שבת? So the גמרא says דאמר רבי
יוחנן תשמיש המטה איכא בינייהו. d'amar Rabbi Yochanan tashmish hamitah ika beiniyahu.
What they're debating is whether is whether an
אונן onein is allowed to have sex on שבת. When he says
כולן, kulan, he's saying something else also you're doing that we're not
that we haven't mentioned, which is sex. Sex is also allowed on
שבת. Okay, so there's a debate on שבת is an אונן onein
allowed to have sex or not? מאי לאו בהא קמיפלגי. mai lav
beha kamifpalgi. This must be the debate. דמר סבר יש אבילות בשבת.
d'mar savar yesh aveilus b'shabbos. Notice that we're talking about אנינות. A,
whoever said that an אונן onein can't have sex, right? We said
that an אבל aveil. can't have sex, and never said an אונן
onein, can't have sex. So A, assuming that was problematic, and B,
that we can learn what an אונן onein, is allowed to do
on שבת and translate that into יש אבילות בשבת yesh aveilus b'shabbos
or אין אבילות בשבת, ein aveilus b'shabbos, right? So it becomes very
strange. Also by the way though in the context here of יש
אבילות בשבת, yesh aveilus b'shabbos, it's accepting that not everything is נוהג
noheig by the אונן, onein. most things are not being practiced, right?
The question is these דברים שבצנעא dvarim sheb'tzina being practiced. So again
what does יש אבילות yesh aveilus mean? Full, or are we talking
only about דברים שבצנעא? dvarim sheb'tzina? So the גמרא anyway says if
a person is not having sex, we see there is some practice
of אבילות, aveilus. אנינות, אבילות aveilus on שבת, ומר סבר אין אבילות
בשבת u'mar savar ein aveilus b'shabbos and therefore you see that this
is exactly parallels the other debate. So the גמרא says ממאי, mimai,
says who? דילמא אידי ואידי דמר כרב המנונא התם אלא משום דמתו
מוטל לפניו. dilma idi v'idi d'mar k'Rav Hamnuna hatam ela mishum d'meiso
mutal lefanav. That's only because he's an אונן, Onein maybe אנינות is
worse, you know, whether you want to say that it's a type
of אבילות, aveilus maybe it's a more severe אבילות, aveilus so therefore
it would even restrict sex on שבת. אבל הכא דאין מתו מוטל
לפניו, aval hacha d'ein meiso mutal lefanav, here the מת has been
buried and you're in the second stage here of אבילות or a
completely different stage, לא, maybe it would be different and maybe it
wouldn't be practiced at all, even sex would be allowed. ואידך... ve'idach...
or the opposite. לא קמרבן גמליאל התם דאכתי לא חלה אבילות עליה.
lo kamar Rabban Gamliel hatam d'achati lo chala aveilus alei. Maybe there
it's more it's more lenient to רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel that sex
is allowed because a person isn't yet an אבל. aveil, Maybe sex
is really only a problem for an אבל, not for an אונן.
Onein אבל הכא דחלה אבילות עליה הכא נמי. aval hacha d'chala aveilus
alei hacha nami. Now the person is really in אבילות. So actually
it would apply even on שבת. So in these last lines of
the גמרא without saying it black and white, the גמרא seems to
be saying how obvious is it that you can call אנינות a
type of an אבילות and learn from one to the other. Okay.
And that's what this large תוספות is about, is about I'll just
try to read you one line of this before
we... Okay. Actually I won't read it. ואינו. But anyway the תוספות
ואינו Tosafos Ve'eino deals with this basic conceptual question which this גמרא
is an anchor for, which is do you see אנינות and אבילות
as completely distinct things having nothing to do with one another, right,
and or do you see it as basically one continuous set of
practices that are done in sort of the way of expression of
mourning with special differences because of the reality of מתו מוטל לפניו?
meiso mutal lefanav? But that you fundamentally still say this person is
in a state of אבילות but there are special הלכות that apply
because of מתו מוטל לפניו. meiso mutal lefanav. By the way, it's
interesting to think about when
does that apply that are more or less severe.
Some are more severe and some are less severe, all because of
the special circumstances of מתו מוטל לפניו. meiso mutal lefanav. But in
the principled way, if there's no override, there's no special considerations, if
you were to ask what practices should I assume an אונן does?
My answer is: I'll assume an אונן does all practices of אבלות
unless there are special reasons to make exception. Okay, and that's the
conceptual model. And then you say, so the reason we allow bathing
and we allow this and we allow that is all because you
got to let the guy sort of take care of his normal
needs in order so that he can focus on the burial. That
would be the conceptual way of doing it. It's very bizarre, I
know. Experientially, they're completely different. That seems to be the conclusion of
the גמרא, but because of the way the גמרא put them together,
it leads some ראשונים to try to conceptually create a sense of
a continuity.
And what's the bottom line as far as concerns of the גמרא
about sex? Is it מותר? Mutar? Is it?
Well, we're going to finish that tomorrow. Okay. We don't know yet
what the answer is.